if you are working with larger shows it can be
very difficult and time consuming to recreate
your rig in the GrandMA 3  3d window but you're in
luck in this  GrandMA 3 tutorial i'll show you how
importing shows from cad programs
like vectorworks and wysiwyg works
i'll show you the workflow of preparing and
exporting this wysiwyg file to an mvr file
which stands for my virtual rick and importing
the mvr file into the GrandMA 3 on pc
mvr is a standard used by many different softwares
and it gives you the option of exporting show
setups from one software to the other in this case
from wysiwyg to  GrandMA 3 WYSIWYG from cast-soft
is the standard where i live but in many countries
you'll work in different softwares like capture
or vectorworks the workflow is more or less the
same so this works across many different platforms
so let's get into it so here we are in wysiwyg we
need to export this setup here i just made it a
few hours ago this is a lot of vipers this
is a lot of auras this is a lot of atomics
we have some spiders and a lot of two
lights and all kinds of different stuff
so basically we want to we want to look at this
and say okay how much do we want to export in
this case we want to export everything but what
you can actually hide everything you hide in
this view here is not going to be exported
but let's go into the cat menu up here and
see everything as we can see right here if you
want to hide something you can just hide for
instance lx1 you move that away our front truss
and it's not going to be exported as our MVR file
before we export everything as you can see here
there's a lot of spot numbers on all the other
moving lights and on all the fixtures actually
and usually i would use a unit number when i
patch my show so if you go in here and you see
unit number one but it doesn't work unless you
use spot numbers the mvr file doesn't look at
the unit number it looks at the spot number
so if you're used to using unit numbers as
i am you have to change it into spot numbers
but this is the case and this is how it looks
and i think we're going to export everything as
you can see here we have some a little drama here
and a guitarist as well so we are going to export
everything into our MVR file so to export
everything we simply go into our wireframe view
right here you can see everything up here and you
go into file you go into export and you can see
an mvr export option up here you have to save
the show first so let's just save and proceed
and it starts the export process and you can see
it's going to export 20 layers 212 fixtures a lot
of pipes trusses objects and groups and everything
so let's just do that and it is suggesting
our desktop right here and test show v1 version
1 in an mvr format so we just save that and it
starts exporting everything so the export itself
goes pretty fast and then we have it up here
this is our test show right here and this
is our backup file from our WYSIWYG
so what we want to do now is to move this into our
thumb drive it's very important that you have a
thumb drive attached to your computer because
GrandMA 3 looks in your thumb drive folders
so basically you want to open this up your thumb
drive and then you want to start saving a  GrandMA 3
show on the thumb drive and you can simply
just open up a  GrandMA 3 on pc and go into the
backup menu and simply just save your show
and do that on your gma2 or wherever your
whatever your thumbnail thumb drive
name is and that is going to create
a folder i'll just show you right here it's
going to create a folder called  GrandMA 3
and in that you have a  GrandMA 3 library and a
shared you want to go into the library like this
and you want to locate the MVR folder you open
that up and it's empty because i don't have any
MVR
file and you drop it in your thumb drive folder
when you have done that you simply close this
one down and you open up your  GrandMA 3 software
okay we exported the MVR file from wysiwyg
and is ready for direct import into GrandMA 3.
keep watching if you want to see how importing
MVR files work into GrandMA 3 there's a few
things we need to take care of after the import
to make sure that all information is correct
and if you enjoyed this video and find it
useful so far be sure to give it a like
liking video supports my channel and it
helps it spread out to more people on youtube
and if you don't want to miss any future
episodes click on the subscribe button below
and click the notification bell icon
that's gonna give you a notification
every time we upload a new video and please
leave a comment if you have anything on your mind
it's always nice to hear from you reading comments
makes it a lot more fun to make these videos
if you're interested in  GrandMA 3 hardware
i have some links in the description for all
kinds of different pieces of  GrandMA 3 hardware
so go check that out if you are interested in
information on models pricing and features on the
different models but let's continue so we exported
our file from WYSIWYG and we are now ready to
import it directly into  GrandMA 3 and it works
kind of simple you open up a blank show or
whatever you want to do you go into your settings
up here and you go straight into the patch it
opens up this window here we just close this one
down because we want to import an MVR file so we
select this one and we go from our internal disk
to our  GrandMA 2 disk it's called that's what
my thumb drive is called and in that we have
our test show because we moved it into the right
folder in the file structure just a minute ago
so here we have our test show and we simply click
import it's going to go through all the objects
and it's going to identify a lot of things and
it's going to open up this merge option here
and here you can simply choose what you want to
import and what you don't want to import but since
we are starting up a new show right now we want
to import everything so basically we just click
import MVR and it starts working and depending on
how fast your computer is this can take a while
so if you scroll down here you can see it's all
mixed up we have a unit number here a fixture
id number here and then you have a pipe and
everything is is into the is imported into
the patch which can be a little bit annoying
so what you want to do is you want to sort from
the fixture id here so simply right click on the
fixture id and it's going to sort everything into
descending or ascending depending on how many
times you click it so what we want to do now is
we want to make some groups because all these
items here is kind of annoying and we need to
get rid of them so we insert a new fixture
we go into  GrandMA 3 and we search for group
and we select a group and let's just
import maybe let's just import 10 groups
we can always delete them afterwards so we
say apply and we should have some groups
down here in the bottom somewhere right here so
let's go up again and identify all the different
scenic elements all our trussing and our
pipes and everything so let's see if we
can find where the first one is right here we
simply mark it all the way to the top and we
say cut and then we locate our group number one
for instance and we can simply rename it to scenic
and we click the small icon here new fixture and
we paste everything in here and we can close this
one down so it's not in our way anymore now we
need to clean up this file because it hasn't
it hasn't selected all the correct fixtures it's
just selected some fixture names basically because
it doesn't understand what comes from WYSIWYG
it it doesn't know that this is a thomas two light
it doesn't know that that it's a mega point
even though it's saying here it's an atomic
it doesn't know it's and martin atomic and
what mode it's in so we need to replace
these ones with our real fixtures so basically
we scroll up and we find where we want to start
let's say we want to start with our atomics
we simply mark the fixture type like this
and find all of them we right click and we go
into the shares maybe and search for atomic and
it has an atomic 3000 here we want it in a four
channel mode that's the top one we select it
like this and now it's an atomic 3000 now it
knows what it is we do the same thing for our
spiders down here we select them we right click we
search for spider and we have it right here and i
have patched it in mode 2 which is our basic mode
we select that one and it's going to replace the
fixtures with the correct spiders as you can see
up here it selected actually the atomic image and
the spider image and then you do that for all your
fixtures for your mega points for everything i'm
just going to speed up the video while i do this
because you don't want to wait for it but it's
actually quite easy just go through all of them
once we've done all this it's time for our patch
and since we haven't patched the WYSIWYG file
from the beginning it's actually very easy to
patches because we only need this for reference
we only need this as a visualizer so it doesn't
matter how we patch it basically so what we
can do is simply mark everything from the top
and all the way down to the last viper here and
we right click and we simply say dmx universe 1
number 1 and it patched all the way through up
to universe 6 address 235 so now everything is
patched everything is set up so basically we want
to go into our 3d window now and see how it looks
so we close this one down we save and exit and
that brings us out to the opening right here
and then we open up our 3d window we click it up
here and we open the 3d window and as you can see
our entire rig is here just as we imported it i
can see there's a few mistakes here the pipes have
moved position for some reason but it looks like
the fixtures are actually in the right position
it imported the scenic element here the drummer
and the singer and everything so this is basically
how you do an mvr import let's see if we can turn
something on let's say 501 through enter that's
everything and let's put it at full and you can
see everything starts lighting up as it's supposed
to so basically we can actually start programming
from now on so this is the MVR import it's quite
easy i'm gonna leave a link in the description
below this video with a onedrive a shared folder
i'm gonna put this mvr file into it so you can
download it and try this out for yourself at
home so if you have any questions in that process
please leave a comment on the video and i will
answer it as best i can  GrandMA 3 programming is
easy to learn since the software is free and you
can work with it in your home at any time so
there's no excuse of not learning it any show
you create on your on pc software can be loaded
directly into any piece of GrandMA 3 hardware so
be sure to give this video a like so it can spread
out to more people and subscribe to the channel if
you don't want to miss any future episodes and if
you want to learn the easy way to build a  GrandMA 3
layout from this MVR file we just imported
i suggest you watch next week's video when it's
ready i'm going to link it on the screen as you
can see it right now i try to release one new
video every week so please come back if you want
to continue learning  GrandMA 3 programming
i hope to see you on the channel again in
the future and until then - HAPPY PROGRAMMING :-)